[Music]
hello welcome to today's video which is
episode 8 of the inventory tutorial
series in this video we're going to work
on creating a safe load system which you
can see here so i'm gonna say walk over
these um tomatoes and get some of these
potatoes
in this chest i'm gonna place our four
tomatoes in this chest i'm gonna place
our two potatoes i'm to put one potato
there and i'll put a potato here
and i'm going to walk away hit save
you can see here that we've got our save
game file i'm just going to open this
actually we've got some collective items
some active items we've got values
um
so this is our chest and our inventory
and how that actually looks in game is
if we come out
and hit play so those items that i
picked up at back
the chest will be empty if i hit load
the items that we'd already picked up
are going to disappear
and we can go back over and see that our
one potato is here in the chest
our four tomatoes and our other potato
so if you want to see how i did this
stay tuned and make sure to pay the
course fee which is one like or one
subscribe and for bonus points why not
hit the bell notification but with that
said let's just jump into this and see
how it all works now as a prerequisite i
guess for this video i recommend you
watch this save data video i did i
explained the concepts kind of behind
what we're going to be doing here so i'm
not going to cover over them i'm just
going to go quickly through kind of the
code and so i do recommend using
watching through this video first that
said obviously if you are a patreon you
can download the files and use the code
or just follow along as i type the code
out i'm not going to be explaining kind
of every little thing i'm doing with the
save system because i went into a lot
more detail with that here and of course
you can find that linked in the
description below okay so with that said
let's just jump straight into doing it
with our little project here so the
first thing we're going to do is i'm
going to right click create and i'm
going to create a folder here i'm just
going to call this um
save load and this is where our save
load scripts are going to live
so we'll open up that folder there and
then we'll right click
create c-sharp script and we will call
this save load
because this is going to be a static
class that we use to save and load just
as a side note i've upgraded to
rider i've not been using visual studio
so that's why the ide looks different
than the rest of the videos but but the
code obviously is all exactly the same
uh but yeah just so you know i'm using
rider now instead of visual studio
so we've got our um save load script
here and as i said this is going to be a
static class so we can call it from
anywhere so we can get rid of the start
and update get rid of mono behavior and
we'll just type in static there so this
is a public static class called save
load so the first thing i'm going to do
is i'm going to add two public static
unity
action um events and we're going to call
this a on save game
and we'll also do a public
static
unity action which is going to take in
something that we're going to call save
data
and we'll have to make that class in a
second and i'm just going to do on
load
game for that
and then we're gonna want two public
strings here as well so public
static
string
and actually these could be private
private static string called directory
i'm going to set this equal to
save data
and then we're going to have a private
static string called
file name
i'm going to set this equal to
savegame.sav
now i'm going to create a public um
static bull method so public static bull
and this is just going to be our save
which is going to take in
some save data so this is going to be
the data that we want to save to file
and we're going to have a public static
load function
and this is going to return our save
data so at this point i think we need to
make this save data so go back into our
scripts and into our save load folder
and i'm just going to um i'll do this
within unity actually so if we go over
here i'm going to right click create
c-sharp script and we'll call this save
data
so we'll let that compile and open up
that in our ide so we've got our save
data here
so you see that these have all stopped
being uh red now
so for our save function um i'm going to
call the onsavegame
unity action just so we know when the
game is trying to save
and we can do string
application dot persistent data path
uh plus our directory and here we can
say if directory
dot exists
so if this directory doesn't exist and
this is using the system.io namespace so
you need to make sure you include that
so if directory doesn't exist
then obviously we need to make this um
directory which we can do here by saying
directory
dot
create directory
so just very quickly we've got our
string here which is called directory
this is save data we're making a dir
another string called der which is the
application persistent data path
which if you've watched the other video
this is our local low folder on our c
drive
and plus the directory
so and we're going to see if this
directory exists
so have we saved the game before because
if we have this will exist and if not
let's just create this directory here
so then we're going to make a new string
and we can just call this json this is
equal to our json utility
dot to json
and data and true so this data here is
the data that we're passing in i'm going
to save we're going to convert that data
to a string
which will then save to file
and this true here is just for pretty
print which i believe puts stuff it
organizes the file a bit easier so you
can read it a bit better in a text
editor instead of putting it all on one
line and then we can do file dot write
all text
and set this equal to d plus our
file name
and the text that we're writing out is
our json string again if you don't
understand any of this and this is the
last time i'll say this but just watch
the other video i did that i showed at
the start of the video and you'll fully
understand what i'm doing here
so here i'm going to debug.log saving
game and then we can just return true
now the reason this is a bool is because
we may want to return false if some of
the parameters
don't get met so for example if we're
already saving
and you could check to see whether the
file streams open or if this file's been
accessed but for our basic case we're
just going to always return true if we
save
for your game you may want to do
something differently and then therefore
it will return false so there may be a
path that you take that can return false
so the framework's there
for you to use if you need to
so for our public static save data load
what we want to do here is we want to
get our string
and
this is going to be a full path and this
is going to be the application
dot the persistent data path plus our
directory and then this time is plus our
file name
so we're going to try and load this
savegame.sav file
from our directory and we need to make a
new piece of save data just called data
and we'll set this equal to a new save
data
which is going to be a new instance of
our save data class and we need to get
rid of monobehaviour because it's not um
it's not actually going to live anywhere
kind of on an object we create a new one
and then we need to check now whether
our um
file name exists like whether the save
game actually exists so we can just say
if file dot exists
and we're going to pass in the full path
if the file does exist then we're going
to
get the file and turn it back into a
json string so we can do file dot read
all text so we used writal text here
we're going to read all text here
and we're going to read all the text
from the full path
and then we can use the json utility to
turn that back into
our save data so we can do json utility
dot from json
and we're going to turn that into a type
of save data
and the string that we're going to turn
back into some save data is our json
so there we go
and here we can say the on load game dot
and then we can invoke this
passing in the data that we've just
loaded
if the file doesn't exist then we're
just going to do else
and we can do um
debug.log
save file does not exist
and then regardless of whether we've um
because we've already created some data
we can just return that data at the end
if it's got to this point it'll just be
the new save data that we've made
so for example if we're starting a new
game and the save game hadn't existed
we're just going to return some data to
get started with
but if it did exist then we're going to
return our actual instance of the save
data
so now let's actually start to um
build our save
data like what we're going to actually
care about saving with our inventory
system
and before we can do that we actually
need to um serialize a dictionary so the
dictionary is going to be responsible
for saving our chest inventory
but you can't save but you can't
serialize dictionaries um kind of from
the get-go we're gonna need to make our
own version of a dictionary that's
serializable so let's just go back into
unity and that needs to recompile
so in our safe load folder i'm going to
right click create c-sharp script and
this one is just going to be called
serializable
dictionary
so in our serializable dictionary um
class i'm actually just going to copy
this in
so this is the code for that i've got a
link in the description
um but basically that's this script here
uh you don't need to know really the ins
and outs of how it all works um
but back in 2013 there was this question
posted about saving out uh dictionaries
and keys and
even though this was the accepted answer
this script here works really well
it says here that you need to
derive a non-generic class from that one
i've not needed to do that here maybe
it's because we're using json but this
just works as a serializable dictionary
so head to the link in the description
you can copy that script into our
serializabledictionary.cs file
make sure you've spelt the name of the
file right compared to the name of it
here
otherwise it won't work
so we can go back over to our save data
cs file
and we're going to do a public
and this is going to be a serializable
dictionary which is the class we've just
made and it's going to be of type
a string
and a type of chest save data which
isn't something we've made yet we'll
make that in a second
and i'm just going to call this our
chest dictionary
and i'm going to make a constructor here
and do a public um save data constructor
and we can say our chest dictionary is
equal to a new serializable dictionary
of type string and chest save data so
now we're going to make our chest save
um data this is going to be a struct i'm
actually going to put this into our
chest
inventory.cs file
so here we can come over to our chest
inventory script
and outside of this class
i'm going to flag this as system
dot serializable so we can save
it out we're gonna do a public struct
chest save data
and this is gonna keep track of our
inventory system so public inventory
system
in
a public
vector
of our position
and a public quaternion
of our rotation
and then we're going to make a
constructor for this so we'll do a
public chest save data
this is going to take in an inventory
system which i'll just
underscore in system
we'll do a vector 3
underscore position
and a quaternion
which is rotation
and then we can set our in system equal
to the underscore in system
position to our
underscore position and rotation equal
to underscore
rotation
so this is our chest save data um
put together
so now what we need is um
so our framework is getting there uh
quite nicely now so just to have a quick
run through so we've got this action
here on load game
that's going to be called uh when we
load the game and so it's gonna get our
chest inventory from file
and we can hook into the unload function
and check the data and find the
chests inventory within our save data so
let's just go up to the top here so i'm
underneath the eye interactable i'm just
going to do a public
that's right a protected
override
void awake
and we may need to make um
protected virtual void
protected override
void
awake
we can call base dot awake
and here we can hook into the save load
dot um
we can hook into our save load dot uh
unload game
and we can make a new function called
load inventory
and we'll create that function here
so this is
oh
sorry i need to get rid of the brackets
so this is going to take in some save
data
and this is going to
check the save data
for
this specific chests
inventory and if it exists
load it in
so how will our chests the in the world
so how will this chest here
differentiate itself from this chest
here they're gonna need some sort of
unique identifier that can say like hey
i'm chest number one
does the save data that i've just got
from the load game have a chest number
one and if it does like can i get my
inventory back please and it'll load it
into this this one can be chest number
two
so we're going to need another script
called um unique id if i click our chest
here in our test project you see i've
got all of these chests here
um so i've got my small chest here you
can see that i've got this
script unique id and i've got a unique
id
this is our id here this is persistent
between
saves and states and scene loads
so we'll right click create c sharp
script
and
we're going to make a unique
id
and load this up in our ide okay so
we've got our unique id script here and
this is going to be a mono behavior
because it's going to live on our object
now we're going to need a couple of um
attributes above so we're gonna do a
system dot
serializable
as well as execute
in edit mode
so we're gonna have a serialized field
and this is going to be a private string
and we're going to call this
id
and this is going to be equal to a new
guide
and we can do dot 2 string
now we need this to be read only and we
need to make our own
read-only attribute
so i'm going to go back over to unity
and i'm going to right-click
create
c-sharp script and we're going to call
this read
only
attribute
and then we can open this up and i'm
just gonna paste this one in it's a very
simple one line class it's just public
class read only attribute and it
inherits from property attribute
so now if we go back over to our unique
id we can add this
read only tag here
and let's just add this to our chest so
i'm going to add our unique id
um field to this chest here and you can
see that we've got our id
here this is our unique id
so we've got this property attribute
which we've called read-only it's just
this simple script and this has to uh
interact with a editor script as well so
back in objects you need to make a
folder called editor and it has to be
called editor so right click create
folder
editor spell like that like editor
and then here we're going to create
another script
called our read only
draw
and this is the script for that so we've
got our public override void on gui
which takes in erect position serialized
property property
and our gui content which is label
and we're just setting the
edit for the property to false so if we
go back over to our
chest
and we add our unique id script onto our
chest you can see that this id has been
generated
but we can't um we can't click in there
or change anything about it and that's
perfect we don't want to be able to
change that code because it needs to
persist kind of throughout our game
so i'm going to save our scene there
so that's our
unique id generated
but we're also going to want a
serialized field
it's going to be a private static
serializable dictionary and this is
going to take in a string
as well as a game object i'm going to
call this our id
database and we can set this equal to a
new
um serializable dictionary of those
types and i'm going to do a public
string id and this is going to return
our private id string here so we can get
this id from other places in the uh
project and in the on validate function
i'm just going to want to check whether
our id database already contains a key
if it does already contain our id let's
generate a new one and this is just
going to make sure that we don't have
any keys that are the same this is going
to be a new method called generate that
we're going to create
and if it does
exist then we can do else
id database
and then we can add our id
as well as ourselves so this dark game
object so now the actual chest in the
world
is linked to its id
so we'll be able to find this we're
about to use this information in lots of
other places i also want to make a on
destroy function so private void on
destroy
and so if we delete the chest from the
world
and it contains the database contains
this key
then obviously we want to remove our id
from the id database because it's not a
thing anymore so remove underscore id
all generate's going to do is it's just
going to do this again so we can just
copy that bit code there and once it's
generated
we're just gonna add it to the database
so this is just covering our backs to
make sure no ids are the same and that
the id database is um
filled with ids and the relevant game
objects
so that's our unique id um
script and our read-only attribute and
the read-only draw so back to our chest
inventory script so we've hooked into
this onload game so now we can actually
load the inventory
so what i'm going to say here is
if
data so this save data
and if the chest dictionary contains
our id so get component
unique id
and from that component we're going to
get the id
then it's going to pass back out
the chest
save data and we can just call this the
chest data
so remember our save data has has this
chest dictionary which has got a string
this is going to be our chests unique id
that we've just generated and some save
data this save data is this data here so
it's the inventory system the chest
position and its rotation so from this
chest data
all we need to do then is just this dot
inventory
primary inventory system is equal to the
chest data dart inventory system
because remember our inventory holder
it's got a primary inventory system so
that's the first inventory system that
all
inventory holders will have
so
primary inventory system is equal to the
inventory system that's stored in our
chest save data we can say this dot
transform dot position is equal to the
chest data dot position
and this dot transform dot rotation is
equal to the chest data dot rotation the
reason we're saving this is because in
your game you may be you may want to be
able to craft a chest like in minecraft
and place it down in the world
and if you do that it's going to know
where
it was like what its position and
rotation should be so we're just
covering ourselves if we want to do that
um
there
now i'm not gonna do that in this um
tutorial series it's not gonna focus on
crafting necessarily maybe that'll come
down the line let me know in the
descript let me know in the comments
below if you do want a crafting system
that builds on top of the inventory
system but if we do get that far then
that's already there for us we can just
read from that we can spawn in the chest
at that position rotation and assign its
inventory system as well if we need to
as a bit of a if you want to go down
that on your own um you could have like
a chest manager that loads in the data
spawns in a load of chests based on this
chest dictionary so for every entry in
here it will instantiate a new chest and
it'll set it to that position rotation
and set its inventory system so in that
way when you load the game first there
won't be any chests in the world and
they will be spawned in dynamically by
like a chest manager based on the save
data but again explore on your own or
let me know in the comments below if you
want me to do a video on that okay so
we're getting close to the end of
penalties actually see this all working
um i'm going to make a start function on
this so private void start
and we're going to make a
instance of some chest save
data so
chest save data we'll set this equal to
new chest
save data
which will pass in our
primary inventory system
we will pass in our transform.position
as well as our transform dot rotation
and then we're going to get in touch
with our save game manager which is
another script we need to make and we're
going to
hook into the data on the save game
manager
and we're going to go to the chip chest
dictionary and we're gonna add
our unique id
as well as our save data
now this is a reference so we've
assigned ourselves to this dictionary as
the chess gets updated this chest
dictionary will will stay updated we
don't need to do it every time we
request to save the game now our chest
save data is a reference type so we only
need to assign this once and it's the
same kind of you know it's pointing to
the same place in memory so we've
assigned it to the chess dictionary
which is going to be on our save game
manager so it will always update no
matter
what we put in the chest so let's
have our save game manager
let's create that so right click create
c-sharp script
save game manager now you may want this
to just be part of your
like normal game manager
uh but basically we need like an active
piece of save data that everything
is passing in its references to so then
when we hit a button to save the game
it can just save this one piece of save
data it was like your save file
essentially it can save that to disk
and we could in the save game manager we
can have a tick that saves it
periodically so like an auto save
function
um
but for now we're just going to have a
public static
save data because we only want one piece
of data to be working with we don't want
to have lots of different save files
everywhere
we just want our one bit of save data
so that can be static which means we can
access it
like this we don't need a reference to
the save game manager
because we can just get this static
variable
now i'm going to do a private
void awake and also this save game
manager class could be static i want it
to live on an object just so i can
interact with it a bit more easily in
the scene so i'm going to keep it as a
mono behavior and it'll live kind of
like a game manager just on an object in
our scene so the first thing i'm going
to do is in our awake function i'm going
to hook into the save load on load game
unity action just like we did in the
chest
and i'm gonna um
make a function called load data
and this will be called data and in our
awake function i'm also going to set our
data equal to a new
bit of save data so all that we need to
do is when we load the game we're just
going to replace our data with the save
data that we've just loaded so we can do
um data
is equal to
underscore
data and i'll make sure i put the
underscore there so this static instance
of data is going to be
um
updated to this bit of data here and we
can make this a public static void load
data this is where we're going to save
our data as well so we can make a public
static void save data and here we're
going to make a copy of our data and
then i'm going to call our save load
class
um i'm going to do save and we'll pass
in our save data and while writer i'm
going to make a public void delete data
and we can call
safeload.delete save data
and let's make that method over on our
um save load file so we've got a public
static void delete save data
and all that's going to do is it's going
to get the full path as it is up here
and if that exists then we're going to
delete that save file so that's just an
easy way of deleting our save just for
testing purposes or you know you might
want to give the player the option to
surface that option to the player okay
so let's actually implement this so we
can test to make sure it's all working
okay so let's actually implement some
buttons so we can actually like save and
load our inventory system and the way
i'm going to do that is i'm going to get
our canvas here i'm just going to right
click create an empty
and call this
save
load
buttons
and i'm just going to add our save game
manager to this object you may want it
somewhere different in your scene but
just to make it easier
i'm going to put it here and i'm just
gonna put in um let's use text mesh pro
buttons and we'll do save
we'll duplicate that and call this one
load
and duplicate that
and call it delete
so let's go to our ui and actually like
sort these buttons out so we're going to
get our
i'm going to parent them all to the top
left
of the screen so we've got our save
button which can go in the top left
we'll bring our
load button down and then below that
we'll bring our delete button
and i'm just going to make these bigger
just so we can see them a bit better
i'll do the same with the text i'll just
check auto size just to bring them up
and then we can name this button save
load
delete
so our save button
uh we can do on click and i'm going to
drag in our save game manager
and this is going to be
uh
save data
we've got our load button here
oh again on click
save game manager
now we need to be able to load the game
why can't we load the data
oh yeah we need a function to actually
um
try to load the data so let's do public
static void
um try load data
and this is going to call
load on our save load system
which it was successful it will fire off
this event and then this will actually
do this
method here so
go back to the game
so under our save game manager we can
now choose try load data
and then for delete we can do on click
save button save game manager
delete data
so for ease of trying to navigate to our
save game
like file on disk i'm going to go over
to our save load function
and
in
our save game when i hit save game
i'm going to copy the directory to the
clipboard so i'm going to do a gui
utility dot system
copy buffer and i'm going to set this
equal to
our directory so that means that when i
hit save it's just going to copy
the
persistent directory path to our
clipboard so we can quickly get that in
explorer so
let's save our scene hit play
so
uh oh we've got no no reference
so what's that
ah that's because this chest
um
the big chest doesn't have a um
unique id component on it
so what we'd actually want to do for our
chest inventory is put in a require
component
of type unique id
type of
unique id
so
when we call get component that's not
going to
throw that error where we may also want
to cache our
um unique id
instead of calling get component but
i'll just leave it like that for now
let's just make sure it's working first
so let's hit play
so let's go over some objects come over
here press e
pick up our tomatoes put them in that
chest we'll go get some potatoes
pick them up put them in this chest
let's um close out that hit save
so we can stop playing let's come over
to explorer i'm just going to paste in
the directory so
tutorial we've got our savegame.sav
we can open this up
in um
any text editor i'm just going to use
notepad
and we can see here that our chest
dictionary it had two chests it had
bfeo41a
and occ ec68a
o8e
and you see that that corresponds with
our chests here so
bfea 041a
occ ec 6
8e
so that's our save game working it's got
our chest extreme it's saved our keys
and it's got the value so it's got
uh item data instance id 2432 that's
referring to our tomatoes
and a stack size of four
so that's that's all working if we go
back over to our chest and press e
you'll see that there's nothing in them
so we'll close that we'll hit load
go back to our chest and there's our
four
tomatoes now obviously there's a bit of
a problem here that um
we loaded the game after we'd already
picked up
these uh tomatoes off the ground
so to solve that issue uh what we can do
is in our save data
we can make a list of items and this is
all of the items that we've picked up in
the game so we can do a public list of
string type
and we'll call this collected items
and we can do here collected items is
equal to a new list of type string
we're going to need the unique id um on
our items as well so we can do require
component
uh get
a type of
unique id
uh sorry not that's not on our save data
that needs to go on our
um
item pickup script
so require component type of sphere
collider require component type of
unique id
and just like the chest inventory we're
going to want to make a um
some item pick up
uh save data so system dot serializable
and this is going to be a public struct
of type item
pick up save data
so again this is there for the if we
want to implement um
you know we've dropped an item on the
ground and we want to save that's
position and rotation we can do that by
spawning in new items we won't use that
again in this script but i'm doing it
for you so it's there if you do want to
use it
um so let's do public inventory
item data
and this is going to be our
we'll do public factor 3
and this is going to be
ours
um public quaternion
our rotation
and we'll do a public
item
pick up save data constructor which is
going to take in some
inventory item data
called data
vector 3
position
quaternion
and we'll do item data is equal to data
position
position is equal to position
rotation equal to rotation
okay so we've got our save data there
and again just like on the
chest on the save data
for the chest we need to hook into our
safe load on load game
so in our
on awake function just above the
colliders i'm going to do
save load dot
on load game
and we're going to do
load game
so here i'm going to do a private string
id
and we will cache our id here because it
is good practice and i'm also gonna do a
serialized field private
item pick up save data just called item
save data so we can say our id is equal
to get component
unique id
dot id
and we can do items saved here is equal
to some new
save data which is going to take in
our inventory item data so
item data
our position just like the chest and our
rotation just like the chest and just
like
we had a start function here for our
chest inventory that adds itself to the
save game manager's data
we can do the same thing here so we'll
do
void start
and we're gonna do save
data
uh
sorry save game
manager.data. and then we're gonna make
a list of our active items which takes
in our id and our item save data go back
to the save game manager so we'll go
back to our save data and i'm going to
make a public serializable dictionary of
type string and item pickup save data
called active
items and we'll do active items is equal
to
this so when we make some save data that
uh
dictionary
is valid and active in our load game
function we just want to see if this
item has already been picked up and
we'll know that if it's contained within
our collected items uh
list when we pick up an object it's
going to add itself to this collected
items list and then when we save our
game we'll keep track of the items that
we've collected so here we just want to
say if data from our load game dot
collected items dot contains
our id
then we just want to destroy
this dark game object
and
in our on destroy method so if we do get
destroyed by getting picked up
we just want to remove ourselves from
our active
list so save game manager
dot data dot active items
dot contains key
id
save game manager
dot data dot active items
dot remove
our id
so when we're picked up we're going to
be destroyed and we're going to take
ourselves out of the active
list and then we want to unsubscribe
from the um
save load dot
on load game
action
we don't need to care about that anymore
so we can just unsubscribe from that
there
and in our on trigger enter
before we are destroyed we can do save
game manager dot data dot collected
items
dot add
uh id so we can
when we get picked up this is where we
will add ourselves to the save game
manager
so let's just see that in action so
let's go back hit play
creating missing unique id let's just
check that that so that's on there now
so all of our items have a unique id so
let's hit play
so we're going to go over we're going to
pick up these items
and place them these four tomatoes in
the chest
and we're going to walk away
hit
save come out of that
go back in
now here we're going to manually load in
your game when you
start the game when like when a player
starts the game you'll probably want to
load then so like when the application
first starts you'd call the load
function
or you'd be in a main menu and you'd
choose a load game
um you wouldn't just spawn into the
world and then load
um but here we're going to have to
manually press the load button
and you can see that those items have
been deleted because they've got picked
up
and we'd previously put them in the
chest so that they're here in the chest
and we could take them back out put them
back in
so that's the basics of the save loading
done players hotbar doesn't currently
save so if i hit save come back out hit
play
hit load it's not working on our
player's inventory bar that'll come in
the next video if you want to see that
make sure you hit the subscribe button
hit the like button if you liked this
video as always the project files for
this video plus early access to these
videos
are on my patreon which is patreon.com
forward slash danpos
if you'd like anything kind of
explaining a bit more detail i felt like
i went quite quick because it was a lot
to cover and i wanted to get this video
out and two people cause it's been a
while
since the last video if you need
anything explaining let me know in the
comments or head over to the discord
server which is linked in the
description i'll be more than happy to
help you and kind of debug your code
with you thanks for watching and i'll
see you in the next one bye
you